Guide to the Third Wave Foundation Records, 1992-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Third Wave Foundation records 1992-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Third Wave Foundation.
3.5 linear feet Extent: 2600 Items
Feminist activist organization that works nationally to support young women and transgender youth. Collection includes administrative files, fundraising materials, grant partner information, photographs, clippings, and conference materials. Also includes restricted electronic information. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
RL.01288
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Third Wave Foundation Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2011.
Historical Note
Third Wave Foundation is a feminist, activist foundation that works nationally to support young women and transgender youth ages 15 to 30. Through strategic grantmaking, leadership development, and philanthropic advocacy, Third Wave supports groups and individuals working towards gender, racial, economic, and social justice. Currently, Third Wave's grantmaking is focused on their Reproductive Health and Justice Initiative, where grants are given to organizations that work toward reproductive justice. Until 2011, Third Wave also operated an Emergency Abortion Fund, designed to assist young people lacking in funds to access an abortion procedure. Lastly, Third Wave was instrumental in the formation of the Reproductive Justice Network, a coalition of organizations that joined together in 2006 to coordinate efforts to work for reproductive justice. Third Wave Foundation continues to be involved in the Reproductive Justice Network as one of the many ways it contributes to building the youth feminist movement.
Learn more about Third Wave Foundation's history and activities through their website.
Collection Overview
Collection includes some administrative files, grant materials, research, fundraising, and conference files from the duration of Third Wave's existence, with the majority of files dating 1997-2006. Also includes photographs and clippings collected by Third Wave documenting various events and activities. Some materials are restricted, including board meeting minutes, electronic records, and audiovisual tapes. Please contact Research Services before visiting the library to use this collection.
Collection acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Subject Headings
Third Wave Foundation; Feminism; Women's rights; Reproductive rights -- United States; Transgender youth; Young adults; Social justice -- United States; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Separated Material
Electronic records originally included in Acc. 2011-0164 have been separated from the collection's manuscripts and transferred to the Electronic Records Server. These materials are also RESTRICTED and require prior permission from Third Wave for access. Please contact Research Services if you are interested in this material.
Contents of Collection
- Administrative records, (4 boxes)
  Various administrative files, including press releases, newsletters, correspondence, fundraising files, conference materials, and board meeting materials.
  RESTRICTED: This series includes folders that are restricted and required prior permission from Third Wave before access.
  - Detailed inventory information (Box 1)
  - Third Wave information folder for attendees, 2006, (2 copies) (Box 1)
  - Cause Effective background information, undated (Box 1)
  - Voting guide, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Sallie Bingham Center, 2009 (Box 1)
  - RHJI Press release, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Filing system, 2007 (Box 1)
  - See It? Tell It. Change It! newsletters, 1997-2007 (Box 1)
  - Funding Exchange (FEX), 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - National Council for Research on Women membership, 2008 (Box 1)
  - PowerPoint printouts on Third Wave Foundation (Box 1)
  - Kellogg/Women's Funding Network press conference, 2002 (Box 1)
  - ROAMS correspondence, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Video story notecards (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Board materials binder, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Direct Action board meetings (Box 1)
    RESTRICTED: Access to the Board Materials Binder and the Direct Action Board Meetings folders is restricted. Researchers must receive prior permission from Third Wave to access these files.
  - Fundraising Materials
    - Support Center for Nonprofit Management (Box 2)
    - Lists of potential funders (Box 2)
    - Fundraising foundations, 1996-1998 (Box 2)
    - Fundraising letters, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Grassroots fundraising letters to supporters, 2008 (Box 2)
    - Letters of intent, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Fundraising, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Grassroots.org (Box 2)
    - Donor education materials (Box 2)
    - Uhuru Capital Management, etc. (Box 2)
    - Foundation materials (Box 2)
    - General giving statistics, 2006 (Box 2)
    - Research and reports on fundraising, reproductive justice, etc. (Box 2)
    - Southern Partners Fund (Box 2)
  - Grant Materials
    - Grant partner flyers and pamphlets, undated (Box 3)
    - Third Wave grant partner map and descriptions, 2007-2008 (Box 3)
    - Young Women Vote, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Feminist Swap Meet, 1998 October (Box 3)
    - Lillith Fair, 1998 (Box 3)
    - National Young Women's Day of Action, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Film Festival, 1996 May (Box 3)
    - SoHo Arts Festival, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Conference Materials
    - 10 in 10: The Young Women's Collaborative, 2006 February, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Women and Philanthropy, 2003 (Box 4)
    - New Leadership Networking Initiative, Civil Liberties and Public Policy, 2006 April (Box 4)
    - From Abortion Rights to Social Justice, Civil Liberties and Public Policy, 2006 April (Box 4)
    - New York Regional Association of Grantmakers, 2006 May (Box 4)
    - Make Grants to Change the World, Women's Funding Network, 2007 April (Box 4)
    - NNAF Annual Meeting, 2006 June (Box 4)
    - Momentum: Ideas Connection Action Change, 2006, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Council on Foundations, 2007 (Box 4)
    - Buscando el Cambio, 2008 July (Box 4)
    - Neighborhood Technical Assistance Clinic, 2006 (Box 4)
    - W.K. Kellogg Cultures of Giving, 2008 October (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous conferences, (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Clippings, 1992-2004, (1 box)
  Series includes media binders maintained by Third Wave as well as other miscellaneous press coverage.
  - Clippings, 1996-2004 (Box 5)
  - Media Binder, 1992-2004, (4 folders) (Box 5)
- Photographs, (1.5 boxes)
  Includes album pages from Third Wave's 10th Anniversary Gala and other events, as well as unidentified photographs in packets.
  - 10th Anniversary Gala, 2002, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Unidentified photographs (Box 5)
  - Unidentifed photographs and negatives, (8 packets) (Box 6)
  - Unidentified photographs and negatives, possibly of ROAMS, (7 packets) (Box 6)
  - Intergenerational Challenge Dinner at Barbara Dabkins, New York City, 1999 May (Box 6)
  - Holiday dinner at Phyllis Rosser's, New York City, 1999 December (Box 6)
  - Shari Sandler event, 2000 June (Box 6)
  - Righteous Babes Screening, Starlight Lounge, New York City, 1999 June 5 (Box 6)
  - Viv's party, 2001 (Box 6)
  - 10th Anniversary Gala, 2002 (Box 6)
  - Young Donor retreat (includes Gloria Steinem) (Box 6)
  - Info Party, 1999 (Box 6)
  - Info Party, Thread Waxing Space Gallery, New York City, 1999 July (Box 6)
  - Girls Town Premier (includes Gloria Steinem, Amy Richards) (Box 6)
- Audiovisual materials, (1 box)
  RESTRICTED: Series consists of restricted MiniDV tapes. An inventory of these tapes is available in the collection's information folder. Prior permission is required from Third Wave before viewing these materials; materials will also require reformatting for access.
  - MiniDV tapes (Box 7)